好的，我们开始吧。谢谢大家的到来。
Okay, let's get started. Yeah, thanks for coming.
嗯，先回顾一下上节课发生了什么，对吧？
Um, just to recap what happened in last lecture, right?
我们讨论了如何让算子整体运行得更快，对吧？
So we talk about how to make operator faster in general, right?
然后我们意识到必须使用加速器，因为当前的CPO
And then we realize that we have to use um, accelerators because the current CPO
已经遇到了瓶颈，对吧？
is hitting a wall, right?
接着我们开始讨论如何构建加速器，对吧？
And then we start talking about how to Um, how to build accelerators, right?
我们还谈到了加速器市场。
And we talk about the accelerator market.
好的，那今天的课程我们会继续讨论GPU。
Okay? And in today's lecture, we are going to continue to talk about GPUs.
但在此之前，我们先做几个选择题，好吗？帮助大家理解。
But before that, let's do a few MCQs, okay, to help you, okay?
第一个问题是，
And the first one,
我给你一分钟时间。
I will give you 1 minute.
好的，那么是哪一个？A。关于钢材和成本，你能解释一下吗？
Okay, so which one? A. So so the steel and the cost, could you explain?
嗯嗯。
Uh huh.
所以IO是12，对吗？
So the IO is 12, right?
你加载A和B，然后写入
You load a load B and write
C。因为A和B是两个D矩阵，所以它们的形状是2乘2。
C. Be because A and B are two D matrices, so the shape is two by two.
所以为了加载A，你需要加载四个浮点数，而且我们不能编号我们加载的流，对吧？
So in order to load A, you need to load four floats, and we can't number flows we load, right?
所以我们可以确定IO的分母基本上是12。
So we are pretty sure the IO the denominator is basically 12.
那么问题是这里有多少计算量？
Then the question is how many compute here?
哦，第二个答案。
Oh second answer.
C。明白了吗？
C. Okay?
正确答案其实是D。明白了吗。
The answer is actually D. Okay.
所以这是我必须要介绍的内容，你们需要记住。
So this is something that I have to introduce, and you guys need to memorize
因为这是非常基础的知识。
because this is very fundamental.
有一个重要的点你们需要知道，就是flops，基本上flop是我们用来统计的一个指标，
So one important note that you need to know is the flops of basically flop is a major that we count
用来计算我们为算子执行了多少浮点运算。
how many floating point operations we do for operator flops
对于Mt M这种形式，也就是C等于A和B相乘，其中A和B的形状分别是
for Mt M for this kind of form where C equals to A and B, where A and B are shape of
MN和BP，结果是MP。这个操作的flops是2乘以M乘以N乘以P。
MN BP and the result is M P. The flops of this operation is it's two M and
有人能告诉我为什么这里是2吗？
P. Can anyone tell me why is why there's two here?
没错，你需要计算乘法和加法。
Yes, exactly. You need to count multiply and add.
好吗？如果你去做这个，你就会发现如何进行多重计数和加法。
Okay? Yeah. If you go and um basically do this, you'll find out how to count multiple and add.
所以基本上，任何形式的metamol，你都会得到这些flops，对吧？
Okay? So basically, any form of metamol you basically get these flops, right?
然后在那一行，你写等于Mmo A和B，基本上就是二乘以八，对吧？
And then on that line, you say equals to Mmo A and B, and it's basically two times eight, right?
是16。好的，16除以12。
It's 16. Okay, 16/12.
好的，原始强度是1.3。
Okay. The original intensity is 1.3.
嗯，好，非常好。
Yeah, okay. Very good.
你想要比较的一件事是将这个程序和
One thing you want to compare is comparing this program to
我上节课讲的那个程序进行比较。
the program that I presented last lecture.
还记得上节课吗，
Remember in the last lecture,
我用的例子是你基本上在两个矩阵之间做一个非常简单的加法。
I use example where you basically perform a very simple add between two matrices.
你会发现输入输出基本是一样的。
You'll find that the IO is essentially the same.
我读取两个矩阵，然后把结果写入一个矩阵。
I read two matrices and I write the result into one.
但你可以看到这个在强度上的响应要好得多，为什么呢？
But you can see this one has a much better response in intensity, why?
因为矩阵乘法是非常密集的运算。
Because metamo is very dense competition.
如果你知道这样一个事实，基本上，当你用GPU来做矩阵乘法时，
If you know the fact that basically, when you use GPU to perform this metamo
用GPU来做元素级加法，它们大致花费的时间是一样的。
and use GPO to perform that element wise ad, they roughly take the same time.
这就是为什么GPU如此强大，
That's why GPU is so powerful,
GPU在执行矩阵乘法时比做元素级操作要高效得多。
GPU can perform Metamo much more efficient than animal wise.
所以这个事实实际上促使了许多现代机器学习模型的设计，
So this fact actually needs to the kind of needs to design many modern machinery models
因为我们真的希望用矩阵乘法，至少在数学上，矩阵乘法比元素级操作更有表现力。
because we really want to use met M because at least mathematically met Mo is more expressive than
一个简单的动物智者通道，对吧？
a simple animal wise aisle, right?
但是它们在GPU上运行所需的时间是一样的。
But they take the same time running on GPUs.
明白了吗？这很重要，你需要记住这一点，因为我们之后会用这个来推导
Okay? Very important, you need to memorize this because we are going to use this to derive
语言模型的浮点运算次数，明白了吗？
the flops for language models, yeah, down the road.
好，第二个，1分钟。
Okay? Second one, 1 minute.
这个很简单，对吧？那么是哪一个？
This is the easy one, right? So which one?
基本上是F，对吧？
It's basically F, right?
除了F，其他的我希望都在讲座中介绍过了，好吗？
Except F, all the others I hope introduced in the lecture, okay?
好，第三个呢？
Okay. The third one?
也许半分钟，这个很简单。
Maybe half a minute. This is the easy one.
哪一个？A，对吧。
Which one? A, right.
所以基本上，如果你还记得应力的定义，基本上就是如果我们沿着这个维度移动，
So basically, if you remember the definition of stress is basically if we move along this dimension,
我们需要沿着行主序列移动多少个元素。
how many elements we need to move along the row major sequence.
所以这里我用了一个小技巧，就是我引入了一个非常简单的维度，就是1，对吧？
So here I play a trick that is I introduce a very like a trivial dimension, which is one, right?
所以你基本上只需要把这个1复制到这里，因为如果你沿着这个维度移动，
So you basically just copy this one here because if you move along this dimension,
你只需要移动一个元素，好吗？
you just move one element, okay?
很好。最后一个。
Cool. The last one.
哪一个？C，对吧？
Which one? C, right?
是的，我们一个一个来。
Yeah, let's go with one by one.
所以缓存告诉我们，缓存并不会节省内存，因为
So cache telling definitely does not save memory on catch because
我们将在缓存中使用更多的内存，好吗？
we are going to use more memory in catch, okay?
它减少的是rhyme和缓存之间的内存，而不是缓存和寄存器之间，对吗？
And it reduce memory between rhyme and catch, not cache and register, right?
好的。能够减少这个的，基本上是寄存器调度，对吗？
Okay. The one that reduce this is basically register telling, okay?
这个，对，没错。
And this one, yeah, true.
这样会增加算术强度吗？
Does it increase arithmat intensity?
是的，会增加，但不是因为它让计算变快了。
Yes, it increases, but it's not because it makes compute faster.
是因为它减少了IO，好吗？
It's because it reduce IO, okay?
很好。就是这些。我们继续吧。
Cool. Yeah, that's all it. And let's continue.
那么今天，为了这个学习目标，我们将继续上节课的话题。
So today, to this learning goal, okay, we are going to continue last lectures topic.
我们将更深入地探讨GPU，并且会讨论一些非常
We are going to dive deeper into GPUs, and we are going to talk about some very,
嗯，Cuda中的简单示例。好吗？
um, simple examples in Cuda. Okay?
这是一个展示GPU的图片，我们来稍微解析一下这张图。
So, so this is a picture that illustrating GPU, let's parse this picture a little bit because
这张图基本上引用自dia，它和你用过的其他处理器非常相似。
this one is basically quoted from dia, it's very similar to any other processors
你们以前用过的处理器，对吧？
you have ever played with, right?
我们有全局内存，还有一些L2、L1缓存。
We have a global memory, and we have some L two, L one catch.
这是GPU的内存层级结构，我们这里还有一些L0缓存，
Okay? This is GPU memory hierarchy and we have some LO catch here,
它比L2再高一层，对吧？
which is one layer upper than L two, right?
我们还有一些寄存器。
And we have some registers.
这就是GPU的内存层级结构。
This is GPU memory hierarchy.
让GPU与众不同的是，你会发现有很多叫做SM的东西。
The thing that makes GPU different, you'll find that there are so many things called SM.
好的。通常在CPU中，你只有几个核心。
Okay. And normally in CPU, you just has a few course.
但在GPU中，你有一个叫做SM的定义。
But in GPU you have a definition called SM.
SM基本上代表的是流处理器单元，对吧？
And SM defined basically stands for streaming market prorocessor, okay?
我接下来会讲这个内容。
And I'm going to talk about this.
所以在GPU中，我们有几个非常基本的概念。
So in GPU, we have a few very basic concepts, okay.
第一个概念基本上就是kernel、线程、块和网格。
And the first concepts are basically kernel threads, blocks and grids.
好的，我们可能想从线程开始讲起。
Okay. And we probably want to talk about talk from threads.
线程基本上是处理数据块的最小单位。
So threat is basically the smallest unit to process the chunko data.
实际上在GPU上工作的主要就是线程，对吧？
That is the thing that is actually working in GPU is basically a thread, okay?
一个线程基本上对应于GPU上的一个CUDA核心或者张量核心。
And a thread basically corresponds to the acuda core, okay or tensor core on GPU.
这个核心基本上就是那些算术逻辑单元，就像你嵌入到GPU里的那样，对吧？
And this core is basically those ALU, like you embedded into your GPU, okay?
我知道我们还有一个“块”的定义，块其实很容易理解。
And I know then we also have the definition of block, and block is very easy to understand.
它基本上是一组共享内存的线程。
It's basically a group of threads that share memory.
所以在GPU中，我们把一些线程分组在一起，形成一个块。
So in GPO, we group some threads together and we form a block.
明白了吗？而这个块就是让GPU和CPU有些许不同的地方。
Okay? And this block is the thing that makes GPO slightly different from CPU
还记得在这张图里，我们有很多个SM。
that is remember in this picture, we have so many SMs.
大致来说，每个SM（流处理器）对应一个块，
Okay? So roughly each SM streaming microprocessor will corresponds to a block and
每个块里有很多很多线程。
each block has many many threats.
这些线程会并行地计算某个给定的任务。
And this all these threads will compute in parallel, oh for some given task.
然后我们还有一个更高层的概念，叫做网格。
And then we have another higher layer concept called grid and grid,
你们可能已经推断出来，这基本上就是连接或者说是将执行相同内核的块联系在一起。
you probably already infer is basically a connection or blocks that ascue the same kernel.
那什么是内核呢？内核基本上就是我们称呼GPU代码的方式。
So what is a kernel? Kernel is basically how we call GPU code.
我们不叫它程序，我们叫它内核。
We don't call it a program. We call it kernel.
这只是一个更高级的名字，好吗？
It's a fancier name, okay?
换句话说，我们基本上知道在
In other way, we basically know like in
GPU中我们大致上是把内核启动到网格上，然后网格再把任务分配到块上，
GPO we roughly launch a kernel to grids right then Griz launches things into blocks and
块再把这些任务分配给线程。
blocks give those things to threads.
在这三层之间其实有一定的层级关系。
And there are some kind of hierarchy between all these three layers.
明白了吗？有问题吗？
Okay? Any question?
很好。就像我说的，这就是一个线程，其实它并不能独立工作。
Cool. This is a thread, like I said, it actually doesn't work.
这是一个低级别的工作线程，它基本上对应于一个配额核心。
It's a los level worker and it basically corresponds to a quota core.
这是一个块，块中有很多线程，我们会将一些计算任务映射到一个块上。
And this is a block block has so many threads, and we are going to map some computation to a block.
我所说的将计算任务映射到一个块，就是把计算任务分配到块中的所有线程上。
And what I mean by mapping the commuting into a block, we map the commuting into all the threads in
块中的每个线程都会承担一部分计算任务。
a block and each thread of the block will take a part of
因为还记得在上一节课中，
the computation because remember in the last lecture,
我提到过GPU基本上是用于
I mentioned GPO is basically for
SIMD，也就是单指令多数据处理。
SIM D single instruction multiple processing.
你运行同一个程序，但在数据的不同分区上运行这个程序。
You ask you the same program, but you ask you the program on different partition of the data.
这就是我们如何在块的不同线程之间分配工作的方式。
Yeah, that's how we split work between different threads of the block.
这是网格，网格基本上就是由很多很多块组成的。
Okay. And this is grid, a grid is basically many many blocks.
那么根据这些定义，
Then given these definitions,
我想问你几个问题。
I want to ask you a few questions.
当我们说一块GPU更强大时，我们是什么意思？
When we say that a GPU is more powerful, what do we mean?
当我们说H hundred比A 100更强大，或者我们真的这样说吗？
When we say H hundred is more powerful than A 100 or do we?
更多的浮点运算，当你把这个反映到线程和块上时，我们是什么意思？
More flops, when you reflect this on thread on the blocks what do we mean.
有三种含义，第一种是你可能有更多的SM。
There are three meaning, The first one is you probably have more SMs.
你可以在GPU中集成更多的SM。
You can build more SMs into GPU.
这正是英伟达正在做的事情。
And that's what media is doing.
我们每一代都在集成越来越多的SM。
We build more and more SMs every generation.
明白了吗？因为当你有更多的SM时，你就有更多的线程，你的性能更好，你就更强大。
Okay? Because when you have more SMs, you have more threads and you're better, you're more powerful.
或者我们可以增加每次考试的成本，对吧？
Or we can build more cost per exam, right?
也就是说，我们增加流式多处理器中的线程数量，明白吗？
That is we increase the number of threads in streaming multiprocessor, okay.
而且每个线程就像我之前说的那样对应着。
And each thread corresponds to, like I already said.
好的。或者我们可以制造更强大的核心。
Okay. Or we can build more powerful cross.
但实际上这条路线已经碰壁了，就像我说的，因为我们受到了物理极限的限制。
But this line is actually hitting wall, like I said, because we are subject to the physical limit.
是的，核心的尺寸已经到了纳米级，我们现在已经无法再缩小了。
Yeah, the cross is nanometers, that we are not able to reduce it anymore now.
明白吗？所以大致上，如果你看看当前的发展轨迹，
Okay? So roughly, if you look at the immediate trajectory,
他们基本上就在做这两件事，明白吗？对。
they are basically doing these two things. Okay? Yeah.
每年都会发布一款拥有更多SM，或者每个SM拥有更多核心的GPU，对吧？
Every year, release a GPU with more SMs or probably more cross per SM, okay?
好的。我们来看一下英伟达是如何发布GPU的。
Okay. Let's look at how media release GPUs,
这是我从网上找到的一个时间线。
This is a timeline that I get from Internet.
我觉得这里有一些你想要获取的代码。
And I think there are some code that you want to get from here that
这是我们为深度学习做的产品线。
is this is a product line that we do for deep learning.
好的。它是从一个叫做P P 100的代码开始的，那大约是在十年前发布的，对吧？
Okay. It starts from a code called P P 100, and that was released, about ten years ago, okay?
现在来看它的深度学习性能很弱。
It's very weak DP today.
但在那个时候，我觉得它还是相当昂贵的。
But at that time, I think it's still quite expensive.
你得花大约两万美元才能买到其中一个，对吧？
You have to pay like 20 k to purchase one of these, okay?
然后我们就开始从P 100逐步演化架构，
And then we start, like, evolving the architectures from P
从P 100到V 100，再到E 100，直到今天的H 100，对吧？
100 to V hundred to E 100 to today's um, H 100, right?
可能到今年夏天，我们基本上就会进入B 100了。
And probably by the summer of this year, we'll basically going into B 100, okay.
与此同时，你也可以看到还有其他几款GPU，嗯，
And meanwhile, you can also see there are a few other GPUs that is, um,
它们的档次稍微比这个H100低一些。
slightly lower lower tier than is, uh, this code with 100.
好吗？它们叫做p4、t4和P80。
Okay? It's called p4t4 and P 80.
所以这是另一代、另一系列的GPU，你可以这样理解，
So this is another generation of another line GPO media build for you can think it in a way that
它们适用于那些对计算需求没那么高的任务。
is for those less computation intensive jobs.
好的，而这个则适用于更常见的任务。
Okay. And this is for the more coming jobs.
因此，这些GPU的价格会比这个便宜一些。
Therefore, the GPU are a little bit cheaper than this one.
比如说，内存更少，核心更少之类的，好吗？
For example, less memory, less exams or whatever, okay?
这大致就是时间线。
And this is roughly timeline.
如果我们把这个和媒体的走势对齐，你就能看到它什么时候开始起飞。
And if we basically align this with media stock, and you can see when it takes off,
大概是从这里开始的，对吧？
it's roughly from here, right?
对。当媒体发布Ava H100时，股价就开始暴涨了。今年发生了什么？
Yeah. When media ships Ava hundred, the stock price start exploding. What happened this year?
我说的是GBD那篇论文吗？
I GBD The paper?
对，GBD那篇论文就是今年发布的。
Yeah, GBD The paper, was released this year.
真正的起飞基本上就是在这里。
And the real taking off is basically here.
在这个阶段，我认为语言模型市场变得非常非常有竞争力，而且
At this point, I think the language model market becomes very very competitive and more and
越来越多的大公司想要采购H100，建立非常大的集群，
more big corporate want to purchase and H hundred build really large clusters,
他们的订单来自
and they are ordered from
英伟达，大概是在去年的2023年，
Nidia and roughly last year in 2023,
英伟达的股价增长了，你知道的，就是这样。
Nidia stock price growth and, you know, yeah.
加密货币也是一个原因，对吧。好的。
Crypto is another reason, yeah. Okay.
还有一个你需要了解的有趣现象是，
Um, so another interesting phenomenon you want to be familiar with is basically,
就是关于Ms和线程的数量，
um, the number of Ms and threads on
WDA GPU生成GPU以及市场的变化。
WDA GPU generating GPU and how the market goes.
基本上，英伟达是卖GPU的，对吧？
Basically, media is the one that sells GPU, right?
但当你想用GPU时，你并不是直接从英伟达购买的，对吧。
But when you try to use GPU, you don't directly buy from media, right.
你实际上是通过，比如说，
You actually use from, for example,
云服务，比如AWS、GCP或者其他云平台来使用的。
Cloud from Abs from GCP or whatever, this kind of to Cloud.
基本上，在英伟达之上还有一层基础设施，
Basically, there is a layer of, uh, infrastructure on top of media,
他们为你构建软件和基础设施，明白吗？
which build software, build infrastructure for you, okay?
那么，对于Vb hundred，这是我们用来微调许多模型的那款，
And um so for Vb hundred, which is the one that we use to trim many,
就像在bird generation中的bird一样，对于Vb hundred，我们大约有80个SM。
many models like a bird in the bird generation, for Vb hundred, we have roughly 80 SMs.
每个SM有两个case线程。
And for each SM, we have two case threads.
好的，这是计算能力。
Okay, that's computing power.
这样你其实可以感受到它每秒能进行多少次浮点运算，
Okay, you can actually This actually give you a sense of how many floating point it can
大致来说，
calculate per second because roughly,
我可以把这个数值看作是计算能力，对吧？
I can have this lumber that is uh computing, right?
这个数值表示可以并行计算的浮点运算数量，对吧？
This lumber floating point operating that computing in parallel, okay?
是的。然后我们快进到Av 100，对吧？
Yeah. And then we fast forward to Av 100, right?
那就是基本上开始训练GBD三的那款GPU。
That is the GPU that is basically, uh start twining GBD three.
你可以看到，媒体所做的基本上就是增加了SM的数量，从80增加到108。
And you can see what media does is basically increase the number of SMs, 80-108.
但是每个SM的线程数保持不变。
But it keeps the number of threads per SM.
明白了吗？接着我们再看H100，数量还在持续增加。
Okay? And then we go to H 100 and we keep increasing.
我们从108增加到144。
We increased 108-144.
从这些硬件规格中，你会注意到一个事实，
And from this hardware specification, you will notice the fact that
每当媒体推出新一代产品时，计算能力并没有翻倍，对吧？
every time media shifts a new generation, the computer is not double. Right?
因为如果你数一下SM的数量，表面上看，这个数字远没有108的两倍。
Because if you count the number of SMs, apparently, this number is a lot double of 108.
但媒体怎么还能声称摩尔定律仍在延续呢？
But how could the media claim the fact that uh, the mores law is still continuing?
这是因为，每一代GPU中，
Yeah, that's because, uh, in every generation of the GPUs they
他们都在构建一些低精度的核心。
are building some lower precision course.
所以他们建议你使用更低精度来训练模型。
So they advocate you to use lower precision to train departing.
我们也使用更低精度，而且当你有更多的SM时，
And we use lower precision, uh, and also when you have slightly more SMs,
你的每秒浮点运算能力确实可以翻倍，尤其是在新一代GPU上。
you indeed can double your flowing point per second, you have a new generation of GPUs.
好吗？那我们来玩一个很简单的游戏。
Okay? And then let's play a very simple game.
好的。你觉得这个价格是多少？
Okay. So how much price do you think this one?
比如说，如果你想用1小时或者100小时，在AWS上要花多少钱？
Like, if you want to get 1 hour or 100, how much do you need to pay on AWS?
现在，价格基本上是3美元一小时，
Okay. Today, the price is basically 3 hours,
每小时每个TPU要3美元，非常贵。
$3 per hour per TPV very expensive.
那么，当我们从W100升级到100时，价格是多少？
Okay. And when we evolve from W 100 to 100, how much?
如果我们按SM数量来算，大概是5美元，对吧？
So if we count the SMS, it should be roughly $5, right?
但事实是，呃，四，y。
But the fact is, uh four, y.
如果我们进化到100-100，会有多少，也许是五或六，对吧？
And if we evolve 100-100, how much and maybe five or six, right?
但其实，是12。
But yeah, it's 12.
好的。我增加了超过一倍。
Okay. I increased more than double.
事实上，如果你去ABS并尝试运行H100，你是拿不到的。
In fact, if you go to ABS and you try to run the H 100, you are not going to get it.
你知道为什么吗？因为这些H100基本上都
You know why? Because all these H hundred are basically
被大公司用来训练语言模型占用了。
occupied by big corporates train language models.
我认为大学里的学生或教职工是拿不到的。
I don't think students or faculty in university you are able to get it.
好的。是的，竞争非常激烈。
Okay. Yeah, it's very competitive.
我觉得今年年中左右，
And I think by the middle of this year,
ATB和所有云服务提供商，他们将会推动B100的发展，嗯，
ATBs and all the cloud providers, they are going to shape B 100 and um,
但基本上，到那个时候，我们就能够获得H100了。
but basically, at that time, we will be able to get H 100.
所以学术界基本上总是落后一代。
So the academia is basically one generating behind.
明白吗？这就是我们正在做的事情，好吗？
Okay? That's what we are doing, okay?
很好。这就是关于GPU市场和云的一些补充说明，
Cool. That is a little bit more about the GPU market and the cloud,
顺便说一句，这是一个巨大的市场。嗯，很棒。
and this is a huge market, by the way, yeah. And, um, cool.
所以我会给你一个任务，就是去调查一下H100的价格和SM的数量，
So I will give you a task that is, um, uh, go and survey the price of 100 and the number of SMs,
我们现在正要开始着手这件事，好吗？
uh we just going into shape, okay?
这基本上就是WDS GPU构建的硬件架构和抽象类型
And that is basically the kind of hardware architecture and abstractions WDS GPU build
显然Koda是WDA为其开发的编程语言
into Koda apparently is the programming language that WDA build for
让开发者能够在GPU上编写代码。
developers to write code on top of GPU.
这是关于Koda的历史。
It history about Koda.
它是在2007年随着MDS Tesla架构推出的，
So it was introduced in 2007 with MDS Tesla architecture,
并且它有一种用于GPU编程的C语言，其设计完全匹配了刚才提到的网格块和
and it has a C language for programming GPU, and its design exactly matches the uh grade block and
我刚刚介绍的三层层次结构。
read three layer hierarchy I just introduced.
让我们深入了解一下。好的。这是一段Koda代码。
Let's dive into it. Okay. And this is a piece of quota code.
为了便于理解，我还在
So for the understanding, I also um, put the grid on the block definition,
这张幻灯片的左侧部分放了网格和块的定义。
uh, on the left part of this slide.
你可以看到，也许你可以稍微解析一下这个。
And you can see, uh, maybe you can parse this one a little bit.
但这实际上不是Koda代码。
But this is actually not quota code.
这是CPU代码，只有这一行是配额代码。
This is the CPU code, and only this line is quota code.
你还记得我们把这个叫什么，对吧？
And you still remember what we call this, right?
它是一个核函数。我们称之为配额核函数。
It's a kernel. We call it quota kernel.
它的作用，你可以看到，嗯，
And what it does, you can see, um,
我首先要做一些准备工作，然后才能启动核函数。
I first do a few like, uh, preparation before I can launch the kernel.
在准备代码中，我做的是定义一些维度变量X和NY。
And in preparation code, what I do is I define some dimension variables X and NY.
然后我定义了一个三维数组，叫做每块线程数。
And then I define a three dimensional array, which is called a threads per block.
好的，三维的。
Okay, three dimensional.
从这里你可以看到，每个块大约有12个线程，对吧？
Okay. And from this, you can see per block roughly have 12 threads, right?
然后我还定义了一些三维的，我们称之为块数。
Okay. And then I also define some three dom no we called lumber blocks.
好吗？我这样做的方法是用原始的形状数组去除以
Okay? And the way I do it is I use the original shape array to divide it by
每个块的sra，从而得到这些木块。
sra per block in order to get these lumber blocks.
它也是一个三维数组。
It's also three dimsion array.
然后我开始启动Qunar内核，Quada内核的语法看起来像这样。
And then I start launching Qunar kernel and the grammar of Quada kernel looks like this.
这里就是你向内核传递参数的地方。
So this is where you pass argument into the kernel.
同时，你会得到这个地方，你需要传递两个元数据。
And meanwhile, you get this where you pass two metadata.
一个是我刚刚创建的三维数组
One is the three dom array
叫做lumber blocks（木块）。
I just created called lumber blocks.
另一个是每块的thre。
The other is the thre per block.
这基本上意味着你将要启动你的内核，基本上会
And this basically means you are going to launch your kernel that will basically
在TPU上运行这么多块和这么多线程。
run on this number of blocks and this number of threads on
好的，有什么问题吗？
TPU. Okay. Any question?
很好。从这个图中我们实际上可以算出将运行多少线程和块。
Cool. From this figure we can actually figure out how many threads and blocks is going to
因为这里已经非常明确地声明了。会运行多少个块？
run Because this is declared here, very explicitly. How many blocks will run?
基本上就是把这两个值相乘，对吧？
So basically multiply these two values, right?
对于这个，x是
And for this x is
12，每个块的线程第一维是4。
12 and the first dimension of threads per block is four.
所以这个值是3，这个是2，我们一共运行6个块。
So this value is three, for this one is two, we are running on six blocks.
那么有多少线程在运行呢？
And then how many threads are running?
基本上就是这两个值的乘积，对吧？是72个线程。
It's basically the product of two values, right? It's 72 threads.
好吗？所以我们大致上是运行在六个块上，总共有72个线程。
Okay? So we are roughly running on six blocks with in total, 72 threads.
所以每个块会有12个线程。明白了吗。
So each block will have 12 threads. Okay.
明白。所以我们基本上是在72个线程中映射社区，对吧？
Clear. So we are basically mapping the community in 72 threads, okay?
是的，这就是我刚才做的。
Yeah, this is what I just did.
好吗？还记得我写那段代码的时候，
Okay? So remember when I write that code where I mix
把CPC和PC混合在一起，我会做一些准备工作。
CPC and PC together, I do some preparation.
在那些准备工作中，我主要是定义线程的形状，
In that preparation, what I do is basically I define the shape of the threads,
也就是块下的三维数组线程。
the three dimensional array, threads under the blocks.
在Coda中，对于那个形状有一些定义。
In Coda, there is a few uh, definitions about that shape.
好的，所以在这页幻灯片上，你基本上就是定义。
Okay? So here in this slide, you basically definition.
我们首先有一个定义，叫做网格维度（grade Dam）。
We first have a definition which is called a grade Dam.
好的，这个网格维度基本上定义了我有多少个块属于这个网格。
Okay. This grade deem basically defines how many blocks I have that grade.
我在一个网格中只有一个等级。所以记住，在一个GPO中我只有一个网格。
I have in one grade. So remember in one GPO I only have one grade.
好吗？所以这个网格维度基本上就是一个网格中块的总数。
Okay? So basically this grade deem is the total number of blocks in a grade basically should be
它应该等于GPU中SM的数量，因为每个SM对应一个块。
equal to the number of SMs, right in GPU because each SM maps to a block.
所以这个网格维度基本上定义了网格的维度。
So this grade dam basically defines the dimension of the grade.
这里举个例子，这是网格维度X，这是网格维度Y。
And this will give you example, this is a grade deam X and this grid Dam Y.
如果我在这个网格数组上进行索引，
If I index on this graded array,
我基本上会得到一个M，也就是一个块。这里就是这样。
I basically get one M which is a block. Okay, here.
然后因为我的块在网格中是按照一定方式排列的。
And then because my block is arranged in a way in a grade.
所以我会有一个块索引，基本上是帮助我索引这是哪个块。
So what I do is I will have a block index, basically help me index which block this is.
好的。同样地，我还有一个块维度，为什么我要有一个块维度呢？
Okay. And similarly, I have a block dam why I have a block dam.
因为一个块有很多很多线程，所以我必须以某种方式组织它们，
Because a block has many many threads, so I have to organize them in
这样我才能映射我的计算。
a way that I can map my competition.
我还有一个块D。在这个图中，你可以看到这个块D基本上是三乘三的。
I also have a block D. And in this figure, you can see this block D is basically three by three.
好的？我把九个线程组织到我的块里的D里。
Okay? I organize nine threads, into D in my block.
最后，当然我还有一个线程索引，因为线程是最小的单位，
And finally, of course, I have a thread index, because thread is the smallest unit,
所以我需要索引来索引它们。
so I have index to index them.
好的，那我有两个问题。
Okay. Then I have two questions.
那什么是大D？
So what is a great D?
所以grade I总是等于零或者一，这取决于你怎么给它编号
So grade I always equal to zero or one, depending on how you index it because
因为我们只有一个grade，对吧？
we only have one grade, right?
那thread dam呢？
So what about thread dam?
这也是个简单的事情，因为它也只剩下一个。
It's also a trivial thing, because it reduced to one.
因为thread是最小的单位，所以我只在一个维度上读取。
Because thread is the smallest unit, so I only for eareads one dimension.
有什么问题吗？嗯，抱歉。
Any question? Yeah. Sorry.
Grade ID基本上就是grade的索引，对吗？
Grade ID is basically index of the grade, right?
因为我只有一个grade，所以索引是零。
Because I only have one grade, so the index is zero.
好的，明白。这基本上给你一个coda程序的例子。
Okay. Cool. Okay, this basically give you an example of a coda program.
在这个程序里，我们做的基本上是尝试把两个矩阵相加。
And in this a program, what we do is basically try to we try to add two matrices.
我想对于这部分内容，你们已经很熟悉了，我已经解释过这是CPU代码。
I think for this part, you guys are already for miliar I already explained this is the CPU code.
除了这部分代码之外，你们还需要实现内核。
And in addition to this part of the code, you also need to implement the kernel,
这基本上就是内核的实现。
this is basically the implementation of the kernel.
这个CPU部分的代码主要作用是启动一组线程，
So what this CPU part of the code does is basically it launch a grade of da threats and it
这个调用会阻塞，
will basically so this call will basically blocks,
嗯，直到你启动的所有线程都返回为止，明白吗？
um and until all the threats you launch return. Okay?
实际上发生的情况是你传递了数组A、B和C，
And what it happening is basically you pass the array A, B, and C,
其中A和B是你想要相加的两个数组，而C是
which is A and B are the two arrays you want to add together and C is
你想要写入结果的地方，对吧？
where you want to write the results, right?
你把这个参数传给了square内核，这个square内核会运行这个操作，明白了吗？
And you give this argument to the qua kernel, and this squaar kernel is going to run this, okay?
现在让我们把注意力转移到这个quadar内核上，好吗。
And let's move our focus on this quadar kernel, okay.
在quata内核中有一些非常奇怪的语法，但你必须记住它。
So there are some very weird grammar in quata kernel, but you have to remember it.
定义quata内核的方式是使用一些注解。
The way that you define quata kernels, you use some annotation.
例如，你会用到global注解，
For example, you give you the global notation which
它基本上表示一个quaakernel函数是在GPU上运行的。
basically denotes a quaakernel function runs on GPU.
好的，如果你用global来开始一个函数，基本上就意味着它是一个quadra内核。
Okay. And if you start function with global, basically, it means it's a quadra kernel.
当然，你会把数组传递进去，对吧？
Okay. And, um, and of course, you pass array into that, right?
但这里有趣的是，当你实现quadra内核时，
But the interest thing here is when you implement quadra kernel, uh,
因为这个函数会在你从CPU启动的所有线程上运行。
because this function is going to run all the threads, you launched from CPU.
所以当你实现内核时，你必须考虑每个线程的任务是什么。
So when you implement uh kernel, you have to think about like what is the job of that thread.
因为我们使用SIMD，所以它会进行分割处理。
Because we do SIMD, so it split works.
所以每个线程只会处理全局数据ABC的一部分。
So each thread will take only a split of the global data ABC.
所以你需要思考，这个线程的任务是什么。
So you have to think in a way that what is the job of this thread.
在这个程序中，基本上可以说，我们做的是利用块索引和块维度以及
So in this program, you can basically say, what do we do is we use Block index and block Dam and
线程索引来获取在数组A、B和C上的索引，对吧。
thread index to get uh get index over this array A B and C, right.
然后我们用这个索引去定位一部分数据，并把它们相加，
And then we use this array to index a part of data and we add them together,
然后把结果写回到C数组里。明白了吗？
and write the result back to C. Okay.
有什么问题吗？好的。
Any question? Okay.
所以这里的关键点其实是，你必须使用块维度和线程索引，
So the metal point here is basically, you have to use this block dam thread index,
通过这种方式来确定你所负责的那一部分数据。
this kind of thing to figure out what is the proportion of
你希望这个线程处理的数据。
data that you want this thread to process on.
然后你把结果写回到数组中。
And then you write the result back to the array.
你还需要处理这个问题。
And you need to also address.
你需要以正确的方式访问内存以避免冲突，
You need to address the memory in the correct way to avoid conflict,
因为你不能写入另一个线程也在写入的数组，否则就会有问题。
because you cannot write to array where another thread is also writing to that why have a problem.
所以我们本质上是在用Perl写SIMD代码。
So we're essentially writing SMD code, in perl.
好的。基本上，GPU编程的核心就是你必须这样思考，
Okay. Basically the essence of GP programming is you have to think in
并且你要想办法找出最有效的方式来划分任务，
this way and you try to figure out the most efficient way that you can partition
并且编写这种SIMD代码。
the job and write this kind of SIMD code.
好吗？有一件重要的事情需要注意，就是当我们在GPU上实现Coda时。
Okay? One important thing you want to note that when we implement Coda on top of GPU
我们在这里非常清楚地将CPU代码和GPU代码分开了，显然在这部分是主机代码，呃，
is we have a very clear separation of CPU and GPU code, apparently on this host code, uh,
这很容易理解，也符合我们编程的直觉。
this is very easy to understand and this follows our intuition of programming.
它是一段串行代码。
It's a serial code.
基本上就是让CPU上的单线程一行一行地执行。
It basically ask you line by line, by a single thread on CPU.
但在绿色部分，我们有设备代码，这部分代码就有点
But on the green part, we have the device code, and this code is a little bit
反直觉，因为它是并行代码。
counterintuitive because it is a parallel code.
它会在GPU上的许多线程中启动。
It's going to be launched on many many threads in the GPU.
所以，呃，这是GPU上的SIMD并行执行。
So, uh, it's SMD parallel execution on GPU.
那么，我希望你能理解这部分内容，我有几个问题。
Then, I hope you understand this part and I have a few questions.
那么，在启动kernel之后会发生什么？
So what happens post launching the kernel?
也就是说，如果我的CPU一行一行地向你请求代码直到这里，然后
That is, if my CPU ask you this code line by line all the way down to here and
当我启动这个内核后，会发生什么？
after I launch this kernel, what happened?
假设这里还有另一行代码。
So suppose there's another line of code here.
我的CPU会继续向你请求这段代码吗？不会。
Will my CPU continue to ask you this code? No.
为什么？
Why?
A，我的CPU会继续请求你后面的代码，因为就像我说的，
A, my CPO will continue to ask you the next lines of code because like I said,
这个内核实际上是在
this kernel actually runs on
GPU上运行的，而这段代码是在CPU上运行的。
GPU and this code runs on CPU.
CPU代码是百分之百串行的。
CPU code is 100% like a serial.
但是一旦我的CPU把这段代码交给GPU专门运行，它就会
But once my CPU launch, give this code dedicated to GPU and it will
继续执行下一行代码。
continue to launch next line of code.
它不是阻塞的，对吗？
It's not blocking, o?
如果这个函数有返回值怎么办？
What if this function has a return value?
比如说，我把值返回给数组X，然后我的代码就是下一行
For example, I return the value to arrayed X, then my code is my following line
所以我的CPU代码基本上会进行其他操作，比如对这个数组X进行操作。
so my CPU code is going to basically play some other operations, say operate on this array X.
我会遇到什么问题？你不应该这样做。
What do I have? You shouldn't do that.
这是非常糟糕的代码，因为有一点你必须记住。
That is very bad code because this is something you really need to remember.
如果你启动了你的数据核函数，呃，不能保证返回的值
If you launch your da kernel, um, uh, it's not guaranteed that the returned value
会因为这段代码会和
will basically because this code will run concurrently with
这个核函数代码并发运行，在这个核函数结束之前，如果你操作返回的RAX，
this code kernel code before this kernel finishes, if you operate on the return RAX,
这会导致未定义的行为，因为你不知道 theta 或 GPU 是否已经完成了你的任务。
it's going to give you undetermined behavior, because you don't know if theta
或者 GPU 是否已经完成了你的工作。
or GPU has finished your job.
明白了吗？你知道这个问题的解决方法吗？
Okay? Uh, do you know what is the solution for this?
在 CDA 中，有一个非常著名的 API，
So in CDA, there's a very famous
叫做 CDA synchronize。
API called CDA synchronize.
所以为了阻塞这个调用，你必须在这里添加 DA synchronize，这意味着你想要
So in order to block this call, you have to add DA synchronize here, and that means that you want to
同步 CPU 和 GPU 的执行。
synchronize the execution of CPU and GPU.
CPU 的代码必须等待这个内核返回，然后才能继续执行后面的代码。
CPU has the CPO code has to wait for this kernel to return and then continue the rest of the code.
好的。如果你去
Okay. And if you go to
Petroc，如果你深入到 Petroc 的底层，你会发现 Petroc 里有很多 coda synchronize。
Petroc and if you go to the lower level of Petroc you'll find in Petroc so many coda synchronize
到处都要确保高层用户能够真正获得这些值，好吗。
everywhere to make sure that the user at a higher level, they actually get the values, okay.
好的。Koa 程序的一个特点是线程基本上是
Okay. One characteristics of Koa program is the threads are basically
在程序中显式且静态的。
explicit and static in programs.
所以由开发者来负责实现 CPU 和 GPU 的分离。
So it's the developer's responsibility to provide this kind of CPU and GPU separation.
你需要编写一部分 CPU 代码，然后在 CPU 代码中嵌入一些数据核函数，然后在另一个文件中，
You have to write a part of CPU and then the CPU you embed a few da kernels and then another file,
你可能需要实际实现这个核函数，好吗？
you probably implement actually provide implementation of the a kernel, okay?
同时，开发者还需要显式声明 block 的形状
And also it's responsibility of the developers to basically explicitly declare the block
以及你想要使用的线程数。
deem the shapes and the threads number threads you want to use.
数据映射到 block 和线程上也是开发者的责任。
And it's also the developer's responsibility to map the data to blocks and stress.
至少，你的大脑里要并行思考，至少要做到 SIMD。
At least, you have to think, uh, in parallel in your brain and, you know, at least SIMD,
所以你可以把任务分配到很多很多线程上，对吧？
so you can launch the jobs to many many threads, okay?
这也是为什么很多编译器，比如 torch.compel，
And this is one primary reason why many compilers, for example, torch dot compel,
它们要求静态形状，因为如果你没有声明这些形状，
they require static shapes because uh if you don't actually declare the ships,
那你就需要做很多填充或者其他操作来让这个形状
then you have to do a lot of padding or whatever kind of operation to make this ship
变成静态的，这样才能把这些任务分配到
static in order to launch these jobs into explicit number of
你在 quaakernel 里声明的明确数量的线程上，对吧？
threats that you declare in quaakernel, right?
好的，这意味着 Koda 是非常非常静态的。
Okay. That means that Koda is very very static.
它基本上不允许你声明一个可变数量的，比如 block 和线程。
It does not allow you to basically declare a variable number, for example, blocks and threats.
明白吗？
Okay?
有什么问题吗？所以正因为这样，
Any question? So because of this,
我认为当你开始编写Ka程序时，检查边界条件非常重要。
I think when you start writing a Ka program, is very important to check boundary conditions.
那么我说的边界条件是什么意思呢？
So what do I mean by boundary conditions.
这里，我给你举个例子。
So here, I give you example.
在这个核函数中，我们做的是控制流程。
In this a kernel, what we do is, we durt a control flow.
好的。那么我们具体做什么呢？其实我们是检查X的值，以及我们获取X的方式，
Okay. So what do we do is basically we check the value of X and the way we get X,
基本上，我们使用块索引和读取索引，从输入数组SMD中索引出这个值。
basically, we use the block index and read index to index the value from the input array, SMD.
好的，我们检查X的值，如果X大于零，我们就做某些事情。
Okay. And we check the value of X, and if X is greater than zero, we do something.
否则，我们就做其他事情。
Otherwise, we do something else.
这就是控制流程。
Okay, this is the control flow.
如果你写这种类型的，嗯，
And if you write this kind of, like, um,
Koda内核不会非常高效，因为就像我说的，
Koda kernels is not going to be very efficient because like I said,
Koda非常静态。
Koda is very static.
所有的核心基本上都以相同的速度运行，并且必须做完全相同的工作。
So all the cores, they basically operate at the same pace and they have to do exactly the same job.
但在这个内核中，你写的内容基本上是在让
But in this kernel, what you write is basically you are asking
不同的线程或核心做稍微不同的工作。
different stress or courts to do slightly different job.
那么Koda怎么处理这种情况呢？
So how Koda can handle this kind of thing, okay?
它的处理方式基本上是，比如说，
So the way it handles that is basically, um, so it's going to, for example, here,
我这里有八个核心，我们基本上会映射到八个线程，
I have eight cores, okay, and we are going to basically map to eight stress,
然后我们会把这个任务分配给这八个线程。
and we are going to map this job to this eight thress.
所以在第一步，我们只是进行我们的计算。
So in the first step, we just do our competition, okay.
在某个时刻，我们会遇到这个E和Ls，我们要检查我在线程中得到的值是否大于零。
At some point, we hit this E and L s and we are going to check if the value I get in
在这个线程中，我们要检查得到的值是否大于零。
this thread is greater than zero.
在这个例子中，你可以看到，呃，我们有三个线程基本上返回了true，
And in this example, you can see, uh, we have three threads that basically return true,
其余的线程返回了false。
and the rest return force.
就像我刚才说的，
So like I said,
Coda是非常静态的。
Coda is very static.
所以，呃，它实际上无法处理这种EFL语义。
So uh, it actually cannot process this kind of EFL sematic.
它不能对某些线程做这个，对其他线程做那个，
It cannot for some course do this and for other courses do this,
他们必须做完全相同的事情。
they have to do exactly the same thing.
那么我该如何处理这个问题呢？
So how can I handle this?
Coda 处理这个问题的方式基本上是这样的，
So the way Coda handles that is basically,
我会让你执行 true 分支，然后再执行第一个分支。
I'm going to make I'm going to ask you the true branch and then the first branch.
对于 true 分支，当我让他们执行时，我实际上会为
So for the true branch, when I ask them I'm going to actually do the work for
所有数值大于零的线程执行工作。
all the threads that are with the value greater than zero.
至于剩下的线程，
But for the rest of them,
我只是让它们空闲，什么也不做。
I just put them idle, doing nothing.
它们必须等待。然后我会让你执行 else 分支，也是一样的操作。
They have to wait. And then I'm going to ask you the else branch, same thing.
可以想象，这段代码效率很低，因为有太多空闲时间，对吧？
As you can imagine, this code is very efficient because there are so many idle times, right?
我们基本上把这种情况称为“气泡”。
And we basically call this bubbles.
在 Koda 中，如果你这样做控制流相关的工作，你会遇到很多气泡。
In Koda, if you do this kind of control flow job, you are going to hit a lot of bubbles.
没问题，酷。
No problem. Cool.
那么一旦我们完成了这个ELS分支，我们就会继续进行剩下的工作。
Then once we finish this ELS branch, we are going to proceed with the rest of the job.
之所以不能这样做，是因为他们想让所有的分支保持同步。
The reason could not do this is because they want to keep all the cross on the same pace.
他们必须在同一时间点执行完全相同的操作。
They have to exactly actue the same thing at the same time point.
好的，其实这和配额的整体情况关系不大，但是
Okay Actually, this is a little bit irrelevant from the global picture of quota but
我之所以介绍这个，是因为，嗯，呃，这里我给出了“协同执行”和
the reason I introduced this because um uh, here I give the definition of coherent excusion and
“分歧执行”的定义，基本上就是
divergence execution is basically what
我刚才描述的内容，只是用了一个更高级的名字。
I described but with a fancier name.
协同排除基本上就是对所有数据应用相同的指令，
Coherent exclusion is basically the same instruction applied to all data,
分歧则基本上就是我刚才举的那个例子。那么我们为什么要关心这个呢？
divergence is basically the case I give it to you. So why would care about this?
嗯，因为如果你们熟悉语言建模的话，
Um, Because if you guys are familiar language modeling,
你们可能知道在语言建模中我们经常做的一件事叫做掩码。
you probably know that in language modeling there the thing that we often do is called masking.
对吧？我会进行一些注意力操作，但我会把某些部分屏蔽掉，因为
Right? I do some attenting but I mask something out because
我不想要那部分的值。
I don't want that part of value.
一个非常常见的掩码机制叫做因果掩码。
A very common masking mechanism is called the caudal masking.
对，我总是关注前面的标记，而不是后面的标记。
Right. I always attend to the previous tokens, but not the future tokens.
如果你想在Coda中实现这种掩码方式，会非常高效，
And if you want to implement this kind of masking in Coda, it's going to be super efficient way,
因为我要检查那个东西是不是在因果掩码上，对吧。
because I'm going to check if that thing is, uh, on the caudal mask, right.
如果它在因果掩码里，
And if it's in the cod mask,
我就会移除那个值。
I'm going to remove the value.
否则，我就保留这个值，对吧。
Otherwise, I keep the value, right.
这种机制在 Coda 里非常难实现。
And this kind of mechanism is very hard to implement Coda.
那我们怎么让这个过程变快呢，好吗？
So how we can make this fast, okay?
这就是我们之后要学习的内容，当我们，呃，去到，呃，
And this is going to be something we study when we, um, go to the um,
transformer park 的时候，好吗？对。很酷。
transformer park, okay? Yeah. Cool.
这基本上就涵盖了 Koda 的执行模型。
That basically covers the execution model for Koda.
好的，然后我们要讲一下内存部分。
Okay. And then we are going to talk about the memory.
呃，这里基本上展示了 Koda 的内存模型。
Um, so Koda memory model is basically illustrated here.
呃，你可以看到，呃，因为你有主内存，对吧，
Uh, you can see, um, because you have a horse memory, right,
我们通常把它叫做紧急系统，也就是 RAM，对吧？
which we often call emergency system as RAM, right?
这基本上就是配额内存。
And this is basically Quota memory.
我们称之为GPU内存。
We call it GPU memory.
好的。那么你知道现在GPU内存的底层机制是什么吗？
Okay. So do you know what is lower level, like mechanism for GPU memory today?
它叫做HBM，高带宽内存。
So it's called HBM, high bandwidth memory.
它比CPN内存快得多。
Okay, it is much faster than CPN memory.
所以为了区分现在的想象系统，我们把CPO内存称为DRM，可以吗？
So to distinguish this today imagining system, we call the CPO memory called DRM, okay?
这是我们上周做的，对吧，就是讲解的时候。
This is what we did last week, right, for the telling.
好的。将来我们会用HBM来表示GPU内存。
Okay. And in the future, we will use HBM to denote the GPU memory.
它是一种由美迪亚开发的内存机制。
Okay? It is a memory mechanism that developed by media.
它的带宽比主机内存高，好吗？
Okay. It has a higher bandwidth, um, than host memory, okay?
所以从经验上来说，这个图已经告诉你内存是如何工作的，对吧？
So imperical, this figure already tells you how the memory works, right?
基本上，呃，CPU在计算机上有自己的内存，而像CUDA设备，比如说GPU，
So basically, uh, CPU has its own memory on the computer and CODA devices, for example, O OS GPUs,
它们有自己的内存，这种内存被称为HBM，对吧？
they have their own memory, which is called HBM, okay?
好的。计算机管理内存空间的方式基本上是，
Okay. And the way that computer manage memory space basically,
我希望你还记得，操作系统是如何管理主机内存的？
I hope you still remember, so how is the host memory managed in OS?
我们把它们组织成页面，对吧？
We organize them into pages, right?
这叫做页式内存，对吧？
It's called page memory, right?
我们把所有内存分页，这样我们就可以索引这些页面，对吧？
We page all the memory together, so we can index the pages, okay?
嗯嗯，但是CUDA内存有点不同。
Um um but the Cut memory is slight different.
它有独立的主机和设备内存空间。
So it has it has distinct holes and device memory spaces.
好的。这意味着如果你运行的是CPU代码，那么ZPU代码将不会访问GPU内存中的任何页面。
Okay. Which means that if you launch a CPU code, that ZPU code is not going to access
好的。如果你运行的是GPO代码，GPO代码也不会访问操作系统中的页面。
any pages in GPU memory.
明白了吗？而且在GPO中，我们实际上并不会显式地以页面为单位管理内存。
Okay. And if you launch GPO code, the GPO code is not going to access the pages in OS.
我们只是把它当作一个整体的内存池，然后从那里获取所需的内存。
Okay? And also in GPO, we do not actually explicitly manage memory in pages.
好的。为了在RAM和GPA模型之间填充内存，
Okay, we just put it as entire memory pool, and we will get it from there.
我们基本上用的是这个API——memo copy。
Okay. And in order to populate the memory, uh, between RAM and GPA model,
所以我们必须调用Malloc。
we do is basically we use this API memo copy.
而且这个Malloc也有一个前缀，叫做Koda Malloc。
So we have to call Malloc.
我们首先在GPO内存上调用Coda Mock，然后再进行quota memo copy。
And that Malloc also has a prefix that is called Koda Malloc.
We first Coda Mock on GPO memory, and then we do quota memo copy.
这个memoco基本上就是把一部分内存从RAM复制到设备上。
This memoco you basically copy some memory from the RAM to device.
好的。这个设备，你可以看到它是用Koda Malloc分配的，
Okay. And this device, uh, you can see it is allocated using Koda Malloc,
所以它是配额内存的一部分。
so it's part of the quota memory.
好的，明白了吗？这是很标准的操作。
Okay. Okay? This is a pretty standard things, okay?
还有一个你需要记住的概念，就是锁页内存（pin memory）。
There's a little bit more concept that you need to remember that is pin memory.
当我们说锁页内存时，指的其实是RAM的一部分，也就是主机和CPU的内存。
Okay? So when we see pin memory, it is basically a part of the RAM, the host and CPO memory. Okay.
我们之所以需要锁页内存，是因为有时候我们经常需要移动内存，
Um, the reason we have pin memory because sometimes we often need to move memory,
在DRAM和HBM之间传递内容。
populate contents between DRAM and HBM.
所以一旦你的电脑安装了Koda和媒体驱动，
So we already once your computer installed with Koda and the media driver will try to
驱动就会尝试锁定一部分主机内存。
pin a part of the host memory.
所以它可以为主机和HBM之间的内存拷贝预留这部分空间。
So it can reserve this part for this kind of memory copy between host and HBM.
并且因为媒体驱动基本上会预留主机内存的这部分，
And because media striver basically reserve this part of the host memory,
所以操作系统无法对其进行分页。
so it's not pageable by OS.
好的，它是被锁定的，其他进程无法使用它。
Okay, it's locked. Any other protests cannot use that.
明白吗？在CUDA中，有一些API只能使用锁页内存。
Okay? And in CUDA, there are a few APS that they can only use pin memory.
它们不能直接从HBM拷贝到主机内存的任意部分。
They cannot directly copy things from HBM to any part of the host memory.
它们必须先从HBM拷贝到锁页内存，然后再让CPU完成剩下的操作。
They have to first copy from HBM to pin memory and then let the CPU to do the rest.
明白吗？这就是Koda中内存工作方式的高级介绍，
Okay? Okay, that is a higher level introduction of how memory works in Koda,
接下来我们会更深入地讲解，好吗。
and we are going to dive deeper, okay.
我们已经介绍了HBM。
We introduced the HBM.
但实际上，我们知道任何这样的设备都有内存层级结构，
But actually, we know any device like this, they have a memory hierarchy,
它们有缓存，也有寄存器。
they have catches, they have registers.
那这是怎么运作的呢？
So how does that work?
从这张图你可以看到，在内部，每个线程都有自己的私有内存空间，
From this picture, you can see, internally, for each thread, it has its own private memory space,
这是比HBM还要低一级的内存。
it's even lower level memory other than HBM.
这是只有该线程才能访问的私有空间。
It is a private space only by that thread.
它必须更快，因为我们构建了这样的内存层级结构，对吧？
I must be faster because we build this kind of memory hierarchy, okay?
并且因为每个块有很多线程，而该块也
And also because each block has many threads and that block also
有一块特定的内存空间，虽然很小，但所有线程都可以共享。
has a certain memory space where very small, and all those threads will be able to share.
一个块中的所有线程都可以共享那部分内存。
All those threads in a block will be able to share that part of memory.
这意味着所有这些线程都可以访问那段内存。
That means all those stress can access that memory.
但是其他线程块中的线程实际上无法访问这个线程块的内存。
But stress in another block cannot actually access the memory in this block.
有道理。好的。正如我刚才说过的，你还有一个全局设备内存，
Makes sense. Okay. And as I already said, you also have a global device memory
也就是所谓的HBM，对吧？
which is called HBM, right?
那就是每个线程都可以访问那部分内存。
That is every thread can actually access that part of memory.
这部分内存可能非常大，有很多空间，但速度要慢得多，明白吗？
And this part is probably pretty large, a lot of space, but much slower, okay?
那为什么我们要把它设计得这么复杂呢？
So why we make it so complex?
这是因为我们想让我们的程序运行得更快。
This is because we want to make our program faster.
之所以采用这种内存结构，完全是为了让程序更快。
The reason we do this kind of memory has all because we want to make it faster.
为了让大家理解这一点，我接下来会举个例子。
So in order to understand this, um, I'm going to give you an example.
在这个例子中，我们要做的基本上就是一个滑动窗口平均，对吧？
So in this example, what we want to do is basically we do a window average, okay?
我觉得在CPU上实现这个滑动窗口平均非常简单，对吧？
And I think implement this Window average is very easy on CPU, right?
你基本上就是遍历输入数组，然后每次取连续的三个元素，
You basically looping over the input array, and you take every three
计算它们的平均值，然后把结果写回输出数组。
adjacent elements and you take the average, and then you write results back into the output array.
好，那我的问题是，因为我们要把这个任务交给da来执行。
Okay. Then my question is, because we are going to launch this to da.
所以当我们开始为这个数组编写da内核时，我们的思考方式需要有所不同。
So when we start writing the da kernel for this array, the way we think need to be different.
我们需要思考这个计算的哪些部分可以被并行化。
We need to think about which part of this computation can be paralyzed.
然后整体思路就是把那些可以并行化的部分映射到
And then the high level idea is basically we map those part that can be paralyzed into
不同的线程上，这样它们就可以并行执行了。
different threads so they can ask you in parallel.
那我的问题是，哪些部分是可以并行化的？
Then my question is what is the paralyzable part?
对，没错。所以基本上每个线程要抓取三个元素，对吧？
Yeah, exactly. So you basically each thread to grab three elements, right?
计算平均值并写回去。
Computer average and write back.
而且每个操作，也就是每次计算三个元素的平均值的操作，
And each operation that is each operation of computing the average of
都与其他操作相互独立，所以它们可以完全并行化。
three elements are independent from other operations, so they can be perfectly paralyzed.
明白了吗？这基本上就是我们的高层思路，就是热点是平方核，对吧？
Okay? That's basically our high level idea that the hot rate is square kernel, okay?
就像我说的，每三个相邻的元素，嗯，嗯，都可以合成为一个输出，对吧？
So like I said, every three adjacent elements, um, uh, can be reduced as an output, right?
而且这个操作是独立的。
And this operation is independent.
所以我基本上可以把它们映射到不同的线程上。
So I can basically map them to different threads.
好的，那我们来做一下。
Okay? Um let's do that.
好，我们来看看这个例子。
Okay, let's go through this example.
所以我做的是，我会从头开始，就像我说的，你需要，用户有责任
So what I do is I start from, like I said, you need to its users responsibility
去区分CPU和GPU的代码。
to separate the CPU and GPU code.
所以我必须从我的CPU代码开始。
So I have to start with my CP code.
在我的CPU代码中，我的任务是尝试定义block和thread的ID
And in my CP code, my mission is trying to define the block and thread ID
以及它们的形状，以便将计算映射到Coda GPU上的许多线程中。
and their shape in order to map their computon into these many many threads on Coda GPUs.
在这个例子里，我有一个1K乘1K的数组，好吗。
So in this one, I'm given array of one Kb one K, okay.
这是一个相当大的数组。
It's a pretty large array.
我要做的是在我的设备上分配足够的内存。
And what I do is I'm going to allocate allocate enough memory on my device.
这里我调用了Coda Mock。
Here I call Coda Mock.
我要把内存分配到一个叫做Dv input的数组上。
I'm going to allocate memory onto array called Dv input.
我请求的内存量基本上应该是浮点数大小的倍数。
And the amount of memory I'm asking is basically, it should be times the size of the float.
但这里我多申请了一个。
But here I ask one more.
为什么？因为我想处理边界条件。
Why? Because I want to handle the boundary condition.
我多申请了两个，因为还记得当我遍历那个数组时，在元素的末尾，
I ask two more because remember when I loop that array, at the end of the element,
我还需要再读取两个元素，对于输出，我不知道该怎么做
I how to read another two elements, for the output, I don't know how to do that
因为我只是要把结果写回去，对吧？
because I'm going to just write the results back, right?
所以我让Koda给我分配了两个数组，一个用于输入，一个用于输出，明白吗？
So I ask Koda to give me two arrays, one for input and one for output, okay?
然后我基本上就启动了我的核函数，对吧？
And then I basically launch my kernel, right?
在这个核函数里，我做的事情是，
In this kernel, what I do is,
我定义了一些全局变量，就是每个块的压力，因为我定义了这个，
I define some global variable that is stress per block, and, because I define this,
我可以推断出我的区块数量，并且它没有被每个区块的压力分割。
I can infer my number of blocks and it is undivided by stress per block.
好的，然后我把这个给他们。
Okay. And I give this to them.
明白了吗？这是代码中的CPR部分。
Okay? This is the CPR part of the code.
我希望你们还记得，这个很简单，对吧？
I hope you still This one is easy, right?
然后我剩下的工作基本上就是尝试实现这个内核。
And then the rest of my job is basically I'm trying to implement this kernel.
好的，还记得硬件的想法吗？
Okay. And still remember hw idea,
我会让每个线程去获取元素，并且每次读取都没有回退。
I'm going to let each thread to fetch elements and ever read without back.
对吧。好的，所以我在这个squad内核中需要做的高层次的事情是
Right. Okay. So the high level thing that I need to do in
我首先要给那个线程编个索引，对吧？
this squad kernel is I first index that thread, right?
然后我要确保那个线程知道它需要获取哪三个元素。
And I make sure that thread knows which is three elements you need to fetch.
我还要确保它知道我把结果写回到哪里，
And I also make sure it knows that where I write the results back,
并且我需要避免冲突，因为我不能让两个线程读取同一个元素，
and I need to avoid conflicts because I cannot two threads read into the same element,
否则，这个值将是不确定的，明白吗？
otherwise, the value will be undetermined, okay?
这就是代码。
So this is this is the code.
我想大家可以花大约10秒钟看一下。
I would like to take a look at maybe 10 seconds.
这个很简单，对吧？
Okay, this one is simple, right?
这是我的Koda内核的签名。
So this is my signature of my Koda kernel.
我必须像之前说的那样用global开始，
I have to start with a global like I already said,
因为这样有助于编译器识别这个Coda。
because it helps the compiler to identify this Coda.
然后我把参数传递到这个Quota内核中。
And then I pass the arguments into this Quota kernel.
这行代码是做什么的？
And what this line is doing?
它基本上是在尝试索引，试图找出当前线程的索引。
It's basically trying to index, trying to figure out the current thread index.
明白了吗？记住，就像我说的，块ID、块D和线程ID，这些是全局变量。
Okay? Remember, like I said, the block ID, the block D and thread ID, the global variables.
所以基本上，每个线程都记住自己的值。
So basically, each thread remember their own value.
你只需要把那个值编码出来，然后全部返回就可以了。
You just need to basically code that value and it all return out.
一旦我有了索引，我接下来要做的基本上是，
Once I have index, what I do is basically,
我分配一个线程本地变量。
I allocate a thread local variable.
记住，这个变量是线程本地的，只有当前线程拥有这个变量。
Remember this variable is thread local, only this current thread consist variable.
然后我会取出这三个元素，计算它们的平均值。
And I'm going to basically fetch the three elements, and do my average.
这里我有一个循环，基本上执行三次，明白了吗。
Here, I have a loop which basically perform three times, okay.
因为我有这个索引。
And because I have this index.
我用这个索引去索引我的输入数组，对吧？
I use this index to index my input array, right?
我从当前元素开始，读取接下来的三个元素的索引，明白吗？
And I read the index from the current element to the future three elements, okay?
然后我基本上把它们加在一起，然后这个基本上是取平均值，
And I basically add them together, and then this one basically take the average,
对吧，然后把结果写回输出。明白了吗。
right, and write the result back into output. Okay.
所以当你启动这个内核时，这个内核实际上只在一个线程上运行。
So when you launch this kernel, this kernel actually run on one thread.
但是因为Kota会把这个内核启动到很多很多线程上，
But because Kota is going to launch this kernel onto many many threads,
所以它们基本上是并行运行的。
so basically they run in parallel.
明白了吗？有问题吗？
Okay? Any question?
很好。
Cool.
这是我们在这门课上要做的最简单的一个内核。
This is the one simplest kernel we are going to do in this class.
以后我们会做更难的内核。
We are going to do much difficult ones in the future.
好的，那我有两个问题。
Okay. Then I have two questions.
我这里总共启动了多少个线程？
How many thread in total here I launched?
基本上是1k乘以1k。那有多少个块呢？
It's basically one k by one times one k. How many blocks?
这个变量基本上给出了块数，就是八千。因为在这里，
This variable basically gives you blocks it's basically eight K. Because here,
每个块的线程数我定义为128。
threads per block, I define it as 128.
我的做法基本上就是用总数除以128来计算。我要启动的线程数。
What I do is basically use undivided by 128. I'm going to launch.
基本上，这个内核会在八千个块上启动，每个块有128个线程。
Basically this kernel is going to be launched on eight k blocks where each block has 128 threads.
那你可能会有一个问题。
Then you probably come up with a question.
哪种GPU有八个k块？对吧？
What GPU has eight k blocks? Right?
就像我一开始说的，呃，今天的H100只有44个执行单元，对吧。
Like I said, at the beginning, uh, today's H 100, they only have 44 exams, right.
所以我们稍后会讲到那部分，好吗。
So welcome to that part later, okay.
但总体来说，这段代码是正确的。
But in general, this code is correct.
一般来说，你希望启动的块数要多于GPU实际拥有的块数。
And in general, you want to launch more blocks than GPU has.
这被称为对GPU的超量订阅。
And this is called oversubscription to GPUs.
当我们写GPU代码时，我们总是想超量订阅，因为我们希望让所有单元都保持忙碌。
And when we write GPU code, we always want to oversubscribe because we want to keep all them busy.
实际上我们知道，在GPU的Kota Bacon中，有一个调度器会尝试调度
And we actually know that in GPU in Kota Bacon, there's a scheduler that is trying to schedule
一个一个地安排任务，直到完成，好吗？
a job one by one until it finishes, okay?
所以，是的，我们完成了第一个内核。
So yeah, we finish our first kernel.
好的。那么先找出一个问题。
Okay. So identify a problem.
你们都知道这个内核里有个问题。
You guys know there's a problem in this kernel.
否则我就不会讲这个了。
Otherwise, I'm not going to talk about this.
事情不会那么简单的。
It's not going to be that simple.
什么？对，没错。
Sorry? Yes, exactly.
如果你看这个，每个线程都会读取三个元素，对吧？
So if you look at this, so each thread is going to read three elements, right?
但是对于相邻的线程，是的，它们会多次读取相邻的元素，对吗？
But for adjacent threads, yeah, it's going to read adjacent elements many many times, right?
所以在这个程序里，我们基本上是对每个线程，
So in this program, what do we do is basically for each thread,
读取三个元素，然后让那个线程处理。
we read three elements and we have that thread.
所以我们读取了三次，总共这么多次，对吧？
So we read three times and times. Right?
但是直觉告诉我，在计算这部分结果时，我们并不知道如何去做B。
But the hall intuition tells me that we don't how to B when we calculate this chunk of the results,
对，我们实际上不知道怎么读取，比如说，这里是一、二、三、四、五，
right, we actually don't how to read for example, this is one, two, three, four, five,
我们不知道怎么读取15次。
we don't how to read 15 times.
我们只需要读取这部分内容。
We just need to read this part of the content.
这里是一、二、三、四、七次。
This is one, two, three, four, seven times.
好的，所以在之前的核函数中，每个t都必须重复读取这三个元素。
Okay. So in the previous kernel, each t has to repeatedly read the three elements.
但是理想情况下，我们只需要读取七次来计算这五个结果。
Okay but ideally, we should only read seven times to calculate the five results.
明白了吗？那我们该怎么做呢？
Okay? So how to do this.
这基本上就是为什么Coda有共享内存，对吧？
So this is basically why Coda has shared memory, right?
假设我们有一些所有同一个block里的线程都能访问的共享内存。
Suppose we have some shared memory that all the threads in one block or access.
我们可以做的基本上就是利用这种内存层次结构，对吧。
What we can do is basically we utilize this kind of memory hierarchy, right.
我们首先把这七个元素读入共享内存，然后我们启动这段代码
We first read the seven elements into the shared memory, and then we launch this code
在另一个线程块中的所有线程上运行。
into all those threads in another block.
因为我们线程块中的这些线程实际上可以访问共享内存，
And because those threads in our block can actually access shared memory,
他们就不需要直接从HBM读取数据了。
they don't have to read directly from HBM.
他们只需要从中间层，也就是共享内存中获取内容，对吧？
They just basically fetch contents from the intermediate layer, the shared memory, right?
所以我们只需要做七次就可以了，好吗？
So we only need to do seven times, okay?
有了这个高亮点，我们来深入探讨一下，我们要稍微改进一下这个内核。
With that highlintuion, let's try to dive deeper, we are going to improve this kernel a little bit.
我们尝试减少内存访问次数。
We try to reduce the lumber rates.
好的，这里有一个例子。
Okay. And here's the example.
我会让你看这个内核大约30秒。
I'm going to let you look at this kernel for maybe 30 seconds.
好的。
Okay.
是的，我们试着一起过一遍。
Yeah, let's try to go through it.
好吗？所以这里，我们基本上是添加了这段代码。
Okay? So here, what we do is basically we add this chunk of code.
其余的部分大致相同。
For the rest is roughly the same.
那么这段代码的作用基本上首先是这样的。
So what this chunk of code is doing is basically first.
我尝试声明一个叫做support的内存空间，
I try to declare a memory space which I call support,
这个support的大小是每个块的线程数加二。
and this support has a size of threat per block plus two.
之所以要加二，是因为我要处理边界条件，明白吗？
The reason it plus two is because I try to handle the edge condition, okay?
你会发现一个奇怪的地方，就是我还有另一个前缀。
One weird thing you find is basically I have another prefix,
这个叫做带有两个下划线的shared。
which is called shared with two double underscores.
这就是你在Quota内核中声明这些共享内存的方式，如果你把这个传递给Quota编译器，
This is how you declare those shared memory in Quota kernel, if you pass this to Quota compiler,
他们就知道你是在请求同一个块中跨线程的共享内存。
they know that you are asking memory from the shared memory in one block across threads.
我请求这块内存，然后，嗯，我将要，嗯，读取数据。
I ask for this memory, and then um, I'm going to, um, read.
我会把输入读到支持部分，然后把结果写回到支持部分。
I'm going to read the input to the part of the support and write the results back to the support.
记住，这个索引其实已经在这里计算出来了，好吗？
Remember, this index is basically already calculated here, okay?
因为我还需要两个元素，所以我要让
And because I need two more elements, so I'm going to ask
前两个线程多做一点工作。
the first two threads to do a little bit more job.
好吗？顺便说一句，这其实不是很好，对吧？
Okay? This is not good, by the way, right?
记住，因为这是I，这是一个控制流，这意味着当第一个
Remember, because this is the I, this is a control flow, which means that when the first
两个线程正在读取两个元素，其他所有线程基本上都在等待。
two threads are reading into two elements, all the other threads are basically waiting.
我等了一会儿，产生了一点点气泡。
I wit a little bit. I produce a little bit bubble.
但这没关系。一旦我有了这个，
But that's fine. Once I have this,
我基本上会再加一行，叫做同步提升。
I basically add another line which is called synchres.
这种同步提升和我之前介绍的Koda同步不太一样。
This sync rise is quite different from the Koda synchronize I introduced.
这种同步基本上让一个块中的所有线程都同步。
This syncs basically think all the threads in one block.
它让所有线程都等待。
It tells all threats to wait.
直到你们所有人都完成了这行以上的代码。
Until all of you have finished any code above this line.
在这一点上，
And at this point,
我觉得剩下的就……然后呢
I think the rest and then what
我做的基本上就是求和的工作。
I do is basically I do the sum job.
嗯，我觉得在这个循环里，唯一的不同是我没有直接读取
Um, I think for this loop, the only difference is instead of directly reading
来自GBM的输入，而是我基本上从support中读取结果，
from this input which rests on GBM, what I do is basically I read the results from support,
support就是这个block的共享内存。
which is the shared memory that block.
明白了吗？所以如果你把这段代码和之前的kernel做比较，我做的基本上是，
Okay? So if you compare this code to previous kernel, what I do is basically, uh,
我节省了很多，就像在之前的block，在之前的kernel版本里，
I save a lot of as in the previous block, in the previous version of the kernel,
我基本上每个block要做三次128次操作，因为每个block有128个res。
I basically do three times 128 per block, uh, because each block has 128 res.
但在这个kernel里，我只读取了30次130次，这几乎是
But in this kernel, I only read 30 times 130, which is almost three times
前一个kernel的三分之一。
smaller than the previous kernel.
而且这个kernel要好得多。
And this kernel is much better.
是的，这就是为什么我喜欢华需要引入共享内存的原因。
Yeah, that's why I like Hua needs to introduce a shared memory.
好吗？总结一下，就是有两种同步方式。
Okay? And to summarize a little bit, yeah, there are two kind of synchronize
同步线程，在同步线程中，当我们这样说时，意味着我们需要等待
sync threads and in synchro threads, uh when we call that, it means that we need to wait
一个块中的所有线程都到达那个点。
for all threads in a block to arrive at that point.
还有一种情况是同步无法同步，比如我们想同步CPU代码和CPU代码时。
Another thing synchronized could not synchronize, as we want to sync the CPU code and the CPU code.
好吗？这基本上就回答了这个问题，对吧？
Okay? And that basically answer this question, right?
所以如果你不在这里同步，你的CPU代码会继续执行而不会等待结果，
So if you don't s here, you CP code to continue to execute without waiting for results,
那么你实际上就不应该依赖这个内核的返回结果，因为
then you shouldn't actually rely on the return results of this uh kernel because
你无法确定它什么时候会结束，你的程序会有不确定的行为。
you are not sure when it will finish, your program is going to have undetermined behavior.
好的。好的。这基本上就结束了我们的第一个内核。
Okay. Okay. That basically wrapped up our first kernel.
有什么问题吗？有。为什么我们有这个？
Any question? Yeah. Why we have what?
哪个块？你是说这个吗？
Which block? You mean this one?
顺便问一下，问题是什么？
What is the question, by the way.
你的意思是，为什么我们分配这个支持吗？
You mean, why we allocate this support?
在这个核函数里，y y 加二，我们会把它启动到一个块里。
Y y plus two in this kernel, we are going to launch it into one block.
那个块只有128个线程。
That block only have 128 threads.
但我们需要处理边界条件。
But we need to handle boundary condition.
记住，我们需要从左到右扫描数组，并且要确保每个线程
Remember, we need to scan the array from left to right, and we need to make sure each thread
能准确访问到相同的元素，相同形状的输入，并产生相同的输出。
exactly has access to the same elements, same shape of inputs and produce the same output.
我们必须处理边界条件。
We have to handle boundary condition.
好的，酷。这就结束了我们的第一个内核。
Okay. Cool. Okay. That wrap up our first kernel.
在下一节课中，我们将要讲解met more，Mt Mo会比这个更复杂，
In the next lecture, we are going to do met more Mt Mo is going to be more complicated than this,
因为我们有三层循环，你们已经可以预测到我们要做分块处理。
because we have three layer loops and you can already predict that we are going to do telling.
我们必须对DPs进行分块处理。
We have to do telling on DPs.
但在那之前，我想再介绍一下Coda的一些基础知识。
But before that, I want to introduce a bit more on the fundamentals of Coda, okay.
所以当你把这个内核启动到dA到媒体设备时，会发生什么呢？任何C++代码，
So when you launch this kernel, um, uh, to dA to media devices, what happen any C plus plus code,
你需要做的是编译这段代码。
so what do you do is you need to comple this code.
好的，当你把这段代码交给编译器后，编译器会把
Okay. And after you put you give this code to compiler, uh, the compiler is going to convert
这段代码转换成处理器能理解的非常底层的指令，对吧。
this code into a very low level instructions, right, the processor can understand.
所以对于dA程序，编译器的基本流程大致可以总结如下。
So the compilers basically for dA program roughly uh can be summarized as this.
所以它有一些程序文本指令，对吧？
So it has some program texts instructions, okay?
它还包含了关于所需资源的信息。
And it also has information about the required resources.
比如说，在这个程序中，因为你明确地定义了
Okay? For example, in this program, uh, because you explicitly define
你请求的线程数和块数，所以编译指令会
the number of threads and blocks you ask for, the compiling instruction is going to
包含资源需求的信息。
contain the resource requirement.
所以在这个程序中，资源需求就是我需要——我是用户。
So in this program, the resource requirement is I need to I'm the user.
我请求每个块有128个线程。
I'm asking for h 128 threads per block.
我请求每个线程有8字节的本地数据。
I'm asking for eight bytes of local data per thread.
这里分配的就是本地数据，就是这类东西。
This is the local data allocated here, this kind of thing.
我正在分配这些。我需要这部分内存来存放临时变量。
I'm allocating this. I need this part of memory to see the temporary variables.
我也在请求每个红色块有31 30个浮点共享空间，对吧？
I'm also asking for 31 30 floating point spaces of shared space per red block, right?
这是内核请求的资源需求。
This is the resource requirement is kernel ask for.
明白了吗？一旦你有了这样的资源需求，你要做的基本上就是
Okay? Once you have this kind of resource requirement, what do you do is basically you
把这个指令提交给CODA到GPU，然后GPU实际上内置了
submit this instruction to CODA to GPU and GPU actually has built
调度器来调度这类任务。
in scheduler to schedule this kind of jobs.
明白了吗？那我们来看看调度器是如何工作的。
Okay? So let's see how the scheduler works.
调度器的工作方式基本上是尽量满足，呃，
So the way that scheduler works is basically they try to accommodate uh,
不同块、线程或其他任何用户在他们的Ka程序中
different requirements of blocks, threads or whatever kind of memory requirement
可能提出的内存需求。
that user could come up with in their Ka program.
明白了吗？呃，用户可以请求一个静态但数量很大的块，也就是，
Okay? Uh, the user could ask for a static but large number of blocks that is,
例如，大于整个GPU的总块数。
for example, greater than the total blocks of the entire GPU.
而且不同的GPU有不同数量的SM或者线程数。
And also GPU, different GPUs have varying number of SMS or number of threads.
但是Koda是一种通用语言。
So but Koda is a universal language.
它基本上调度所有这些事情。
It basically schedule all these kind of things.
好吗？所以这种调度方式基本上是，它有一个假设，就是，
Okay? So the way this schedule is basically, uh it has a crestin that is, uh,
线程块可以以任何顺序执行。
the thread blocks can be executed in any order.
对，这个假设很合理，因为你的代码应该是AMD的，对吧？
Right. This is a very reasonable assumption because your code is supposed to be AMD, right?
因为每个线程基本上都是独立执行的。
Uh, because each thread basically asks you independently.
所以这个假设是很合理的。
So this assumption is quite reasonable.
好的，然后TPO要做的就是把线程块映射到核心上。
Okay? And then what the TPO does is going to map the thread blocks to cross,
使用动态扩展策略，我们试图满足你的资源需求。
uh using a dynamic scaling policy that were trying to fulfill your resource requirement.
好吗？那我们来看这个例子。
Okay? So basically let's see this example.
这是我们的窗口求和，对吧？
This is our Window sum, right?
C和D是等价的，对吗？
C we D equivalently, okay?
我们尝试将内核调度到许多许多的考试中。
And we try to schedule the kernel to many many exams.
好的，我们要做的基本上是，我们有这段代码，还有一个GPU。
Okay. What we do is basically, um, we have this code here, and we have a GPU.
假设我们有一个只有两个SM的GPU。
Suppose we have a GPU with only two SMs.
好吗？下面给出了相关规格。
Okay? And the specs are given below.
如果你稍微看一下这个规格，你会发现我们有两个SM。
So if you uh, slightly read this spec, you can see, we have two SMs.
我们在这个SM里有一些线程，这个SM的共享内存空间等于1.5千字节。
We have a few stress in this stem this SM has shared memory space equal to 1.5 kilobytes.
好的，非常小。
Okay, very small.
那么，Koda会如何安排这个任务呢？
Okay, so how will Koda schedule this job?
那我们来一步步看看。首先，主机会把Koda内核指令发送到TPU设备，对吧？
So let's go through them. So first, the host sends Koda kernel instruction to TPU devices. Okay?
然后调度器基本上会把第零块映射到
And then scheduler basically maps the block zero to
物理SM零，也就是第一个流处理器。
the physical SM zero to the first streaming processor.
它会从这个流处理器中预留一些资源。
And it will reserve a few resources from this streaming processor.
那会预留多少资源呢？
So how many resources reserve?
因为正如我刚才说的，之前编译的指令说我需要128个线程，
Because as I said, the previous compiled instruction said I need 128 threads,
我还大概需要，
and I also need roughly uh,
420字节的共享内存，对吧。
420 bytes of shared memory, right.
所以它基本上会根据资源为这批作业进行分配。
So it will basically split these per resources for this block of jobs.
然后因为你请求了很多很多个区块，对吧，记得，
And then because you are asking for many, many blocks, right, remember,
你请求了八个关键区块。
you are asking for eight key blocks.
但是我只有两个区块。我该怎么办。
So but I only have two blocks. What I do.
我做的基本上是，我会一个一个地安排它们，好吗？
What I do is basically, I'm going to schedule the one by one, okay?
我会把下一个区块分配给第二个执行单元，好吗？
I'm going to launch the next block to the second exam, okay?
然后我把第三个区块分配给第一个执行单元，对吧，因为我还有空间。
And then I launch the third block to the first AM, right, because I still have space.
然后我启动了我的第一个区块。
And then I launched my first one.
好的，这个时候，
Okay. Then at this point,
我发现，你可以看到这里的内存已经满了，
I find that, um, you can see the memory here is already full,
因为每个作业块都会请求，嗯，430。
because each block of job is going to ask for, um, 430.
但是我的总SM只有1.5千字节的共享内存。
But my total SM only has a shared memory of 1.5 kilobyt.
所以当我尝试调度第五个作业时，
So when I try to schedule my fifth job,
我发现没有空间了。
I find I don't have space.
这基本上被称为超额分配。
This is basically called oversubscription.
这意味着Koda会把剩下的块放到队列里。
That means that Koda is going to put the rest of blocks in queue.
它会等这个块执行完，然后继续不断地启动新的块。
It's going to wait for this block to finish and continue launch and launch launch.
这样，你就可以保持
In this way, you can keep the
GPU的利用率始终很高。
GPU utilization always high.
明白了吗？这就是Koda的调度方式，有什么问题吗？
Okay? This is how Koda schedule works, okay? Any question? Yeah.
Sorry? It's basically in media driver.
Yeah. Not in CPU, yeah, yeah.
Okay. Yeah, this is what I just explained.
So basically, you have to queue all the block jobs and launch it one by one depending
on the available resources.
And you can see this is pretty advanced because if you look at today's cluster scheduler,
for example, Copernint slurm, and they basically use very similar things.
Yeah. Okay, that's pretty much wrap up all the deep technical contents of today.
Then we have some other things to talk about, okay?
So let's look at how media evolves your GPOs, okay?
这是一款非常著名的GPU GTX 80系列。
So this is a very famous GPU GTX line 80.
我想你们很多人可能是为了玩游戏而购买了这款显卡，对吧。
I think many of you probably purchase this for your GGiveF playing games, okay.
这款显卡同样也可以用于深度学习。
And this can also be used for deep learning.
现在你们已经了解了SM和压力，我们可以从更底层来看一下它的规格。
Um, because now you understand SMs and the stress, we can look at the specs, right at lower level.
这款GPU大约只有16个SM。
So for this GPU you roughly only have 16 SMs.
数量非常少，如果你还记得的话，
Okay. We very small number because if you remember,
H100有144个，对吧？
H 100 is 144, right? Okay.
至于共享内存，就是你这个block里有多少内存线程，
And for shared memory, that is how many memory threads in your block here,
它只有96KB，非常小。
it only has 96 kilobytes very small,
每个SM大约可以提供2000个线程。
ESM can offer you roughly two k threads,
ESM实际上有128个四分之一交叉点。
ESM physically have 128 quarter cross.
那只是一个规格，但这里你会遇到一个问题。
That is a spec, but here you spawn a problem.
那么为什么交叉点的数量不等于线程的数量呢？
So why the number of cross is not equal to number of threats?
因为我说过，每个核心，每个线程都会在一个核心上请求你。
Because I said each core, each thread is going to ask you on one core.
好吧，这部分我没有讲到，所以请查阅相关资料。
Okay, this is a part that I didn't cover, so please check out the readings.
在Koda中，你可以创建比物理核心更多的线程。
In Koda, you can create more threads than physical core.
这里有一个warp的概念，你必须理解这一部分。
There's one concept rap and you have to understand the part.
但那太深入了，因为通常如果你不用warp的概念，
But that is too deep because normally, if you don't use the concept of rap,
你依然可以写出非常高效的Koda代码。
you can still write pretty efficient quota code.
但如果你想达到极致的性能，就必须理解warp。明白了吗？
But if you want to go to the level of flash in three, you have to understand rap. Cool.
这有点更深入了，但试着自己想一想，好吗？
That is a little bit further, but try to figure this out by yourself, okay.
然后我们来比较一下这个游戏显卡和H100，对吧？
And then let's compare this gaming GPO with H 100, right?
媒体所做的基本上是，你可以看到这个thresher block没有变化，
What the media does is basically, you can see this thresher block is unchanged,
还是两千，配额交叉也变了，还是128。
still two k, quota cross changed, still 128.
但共享内存变化很大。
But shared memory changes a lot.
例如，当他们从最初的GTX发展到A100时，
For example, when they evolve this from the original GTX to A 100,
我们几乎把共享内存翻了一倍。
we almost double the shared memory.
但当我们从E100发展到H100时，几乎只增加了1.5倍，并没有翻倍。
But when we evolved from E 100 to H 100, we almost increased by 1.5, not double.
我们一直在增加共享内存。
We keep increasing the the shared memory.
共享内存还有另一个名字，叫做SRAM。
There's another name for shared memory, it's called SRAM.
如果你参加了上一节课，你可能已经知道，
If you attend the last lecture, you probably know,
SRAM是语言模型推理中非常关键的资源。
SRAM is a very critical resources for for language model inference.
这就是为什么媒体在从100到几百演进时，他们会尝试增加SRAM。
That's why media, when they evolve from 100 to hundred, they try to increase SRAM.
我们将会讲解为什么SRAM对语言模型加速器如此重要。
We are going to cover why this SRAM is so critical for language model infracelaor.
但从这个趋势可以看出，媒体正在努力增加SRAM内存，
But from this trend, you can see media is trying to increase the SRAM memory,
同时SM也明显大幅增加，几乎是原来的十倍。
also the SM apparently greatly increased, almost ten times.
因此，算力（flops）也大幅提升。
And as a result, the flops increase a lot.
这些算力的提升主要来自于从普通的配额核心转变为张量核心。
And these flops many comes from changing from normal Quota cre into tenser core.
还记得张量核心吗？
Still remember tender core tender
张量核心非常擅长矩阵乘法，并且它只能做矩阵乘法。
Core is very good at Mtmo, and it can only do meto.
好的，那为什么能量这么快呢？
Okay, so why energy is so fast?
我把这个问题留给你们。好吧，我有一些阅读材料，如果你们去读，就会明白了。
I will leave this to you. Okay, I have readings, and if you do readings, you will understand.
好的，那我们试着回顾一下我在上一节课讲过的内容。
Okay. Then let's try to echo what I said in the last lecture.
记住，在上一节课里，
Remember, in last lecture,
我讲过加速器市场，对吧？
I talk about accelerator market, right?
有一家叫做
So there's a company called
Grock的公司，这家公司很疯狂，因为他们的语言模型推理速度
Grock that company is crazy because their language model inference speed
基本上是Medius的十倍甚至二十倍。
is basically ten or 20 times medius.
我跟你们说过，他们对加速器的配置做了一些调整。
And I basically tell you that they do some kind of adjustment on the accelerator configuration.
那么这个调整是什么？现在你们应该明白了。
So what is that adjustment? Now you understand.
基本上他们也有23兆字节的容量。
It's basically like they have 23 megabytes of as well.
所以对于每个流式多处理器来说，几乎是
So for each streaming multiprocessor, they almost 100 times
共享内存的1000倍，相比于GPU来说。
the uh 1,000 times of the shared memory, compared to GPU.
这个芯片有个奇怪的地方，就是它没有HBM。
And one weird thing about this chip is that they don't have HBM.
它们只有SRM，好像根本不在乎HBM。
They only have SRM. Like, they don't care about HBM.
大部分内存，他们只在
The large part of memory, they only build
这个芯片里集成了SRM。
SRM into this chip.
正如我刚才说的，SRM是语言模型推理中的关键资源，
And because as I said, SRM is a critical resources language model inference,
这基本上解释了为什么它在语言模型推理上这么快，好吗？
that basically explains why it is so fast at language model inference, okay?
好的，这就是我今天要讲的全部内容。
Okay, then that's pretty much what I have today.
下课后我有三个问题要问你。
I have three questions for you after class.
好的。我认为你可以在阅读材料中找到大部分答案。
Okay. I think you can find most of the answers in reading.
第一个是，B 100 怎么样，对吗？
One is, how about B 100, right?
这个我已经在上次讲座里讲过了。
I already left this to last lecture.
第二个是，tentercre 是怎么工作的？
Second is how does the tentercre works?
第三个是，为什么 SM 里的 umber physical course 不等于 lumber active threats？
Third one is why the umber physical course is not equal to the lumber active threats in SM.
好吗？谢谢你。
Okay? Thank you.
嗯
H